<section title="JmolApplet deployment">
  <section
   title="For the applet, what must be installed on web client machines?">
    <p>
      No special Jmol-specific software needs to be installed
      on the client machines.
    </p>
    <p>
      Client machines do not need anything other than a web browser
      that supports Java. 
      When a client visits a web page containing the JmolApplet, the
      applet gets automatically downloaded from the web server and
      executed.
    </p>
    <p>
      The JmolApplet runs as an <b>untrusted</b> applet. The applet
      does not any confirmation from the user to load and begin
      execution. 
    </p>
  </section>
  
  <section
   title="Can the JmolApplet be permanently installed locally,
   like a plug-in?">
    <p>No</p>
    <p>
      Applets get cached in the local browser cache. Subsequent uses of
      the the	applet will pull the applet from the cache
      (after confirming that the date/time/size have not changed
      on the web server). At least, that's the theory ...
      and it works correctly on the browsers I have seen :-)
    </p>
  </section>

  <section title="Use SQUARE applets">
    <p>
      Applets should generally be <i>square</i> ... width == height.
    </p>
    <p>
      This is because the molecule will be automatically scaled so
      that it fits within the smaller of the two dimensions.
      The the other pixels will never be used (unless zoom is used).
      Nevertheless, those pixels must be cleared to the background
      color each time the window is repainted. This clearing is
      a relatively expensive operation.
    </p>
  </section>

  <section title="Use FIXED pixel width &amp; height, not percentages">
    <p>
      <code>&lt;applet ... width='{n}' height='{n}' ... &gt;</code>
      where {n} = 300, 400, 600 ... you get the idea. 
    </p>
    <p>
      While most browsers allow you to specify applet width and
      height in percentages, in practice this causes many problems.
      It tends to generate lots of bugs during window resize
      operations.
    </p>
  </section>
  
  <section title="what MIME types must be installed on the server?">
    <p>
      None.
    </p>
    <p>
      Applets do not get associated with MIME types in the same way that
      plugins do. While the Chime <i>plugin</i> requires configuration
      of the web server, the Jmol<i>Applet</i> does not.
    </p>
  </section>


</section>    

