<section title="JmolApplet deployment">
  <section
   title="For the applet, what must be installed on web client machines?">
    <p>
      No special Jmol-specific software needs to be installed
      on the client machines.
    </p>
    <p>
      Client machines do not need anything other than a web browser
      that supports Java. 
      When a client visits a web page containing the JmolApplet, the
      applet gets automatically downloaded from the web server and
      executed.
    </p>
    <p>
      The JmolApplet runs as an <b>untrusted</b> applet. The applet
      does not any confirmation from the user to load and begin
      execution. 
    </p>
  </section>
  
  <section
   title="Can the JmolApplet be permanently installed locally,
   like a plug-in?">
    <p>No</p>
    <p>
      Applets get cached in the local browser cache. Subsequent uses of
      the the applet will pull the applet from the cache
      (after confirming that the date/time/size have not changed
      on the web server). At least, that's the theory ...
      and it works correctly on the browsers I have seen :-)
    </p>
    <p>
      <i>
	Note that I am investigating several schemes to address this
	request. I think it is possible to come up with a scheme
	that would allow local installation to facilitate offline use.
	The problem areas are 1) complexity for end-users associated
	with a local installation, and 2) version control problems
	when different web sites use different versions of the Jmol
	applet.
      </i>
    </p>
  </section>

  <section title="Use SQUARE applets">
    <p>
      Applets should generally be <i>square</i> ... width == height.
    </p>
    <p>
      This is because the molecule will be automatically scaled so
      that it fits within the smaller of the two dimensions.
      The the other pixels will never be used (unless zoom is used).
      Nevertheless, those pixels must be cleared to the background
      color each time the window is repainted. This clearing is
      a relatively expensive operation.
    </p>
  </section>

  <section title="Use FIXED pixel width &amp; height, not percentages">
    <p>
      <code>&lt;applet ... width='{n}' height='{n}' ... &gt;</code>
      where {n} = 300, 400, 600 ... you get the idea. 
    </p>
    <p>
      While most browsers allow you to specify applet width and
      height in percentages, in practice this causes many problems.
      It tends to trigger lots of browser bugs during window resize
      operations.
    </p>
  </section>
  
  <section title="What MIME types must be installed on the server?">
    <p>
      None.
    </p>
    <p>
      Applets do not get associated with MIME types in the same way that
      plugins do. While the Chime <i>plugin</i> requires configuration
      of the web server, the Jmol<i>Applet</i> does not.
    </p>
  </section>

  <section title="Should I use APPLET, OBJECT or EMBED for my html tag?">
    <p>
      You should always use the <code>APPLET</code> tag.
    </p>
    <p>
      <i>
	Do not be confused by the Sun Java Plug-in developer documentation!
      </i>
    </p>
    <p>
      Unfortunately, the Sun Java Plug-in documentation does not do a good
      job of explaining the current state of the world. The doc was written
      several years ago and really needs to be cleaned up. In many places
      it still seems to recommend the use of the <code>OBJECT</code> tag.
      That is the way things used to be up until about 2002.
      Since then the Sun Java
      Plug-in has had direct support for the <code>APPLET</code>
      tag on Microsoft
      Internet Explorer, and this issue has essentially gone away.
      However, Sun needs to maintain the doc for legacy corporate intranet
      applications that were deployed using the <code>OBJECT</code> tag. 
    </p>
    <p>
      Chapter 12 of the Sun Java Plug-in developer guide says:<br/>
      With Internet Explorer it is recommended that you use the
      APPLET tag for internet deployment.<br/>
      ...<br/>
      With Netscape it is recommended that you use the
      APPLET tag for internet deployment.
    </p>
  </section>

</section>    

