<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<document>
  <body>
    <title>History</title>
    
    <section title="The origins of Jmol">

      <p>
        Jmol was originally intended to be a fully functional replacement for
        XMol which was a molecular viewing program developed at the Minnesota
        Supercomputer Center. Although the program executables were
        distributed, the source code was not available to users, and since the
        program has not been maintained, the free binary versions have become
        obsolete. For example, the SGI version of XMol does not run on IRIX 6.x
        because IRIX has switched to a new executable format.
      </p>
      
      <p>
        XMol's demise left a need for a similar tool. Dan Gezelter, the
        originator of Jmol, chose to avoid the same problems by making
        Jmol open source.  Although it has not completely met the goal
	of functionally replacing XMol, Jmol duplicates many
        of the most useful features, and in some ways, it has surpassed XMol
        functionality. In time, Jmol was hoped to include even more advanced
        features.
      </p>

      <p>
        Jmol was started as an OpenScience project which is dedicated to
        writing and releasing free and open source scientific software.
	For more information about the OpenScience project, go to
        <url>http://www.openscience.org/</url>.
      </p>
    </section>

    <section title="Jmol grows">
      
      <p>
        Later, Bradley A. Smith took over the project and did a lot of work in 
        streamlining the project as well as the software. Under his leadership
        new releases found its way to the user base, and many new features were
        added, some of which contributed by users.
      </p>
      
      <p>
	In the end of 2002, Egon Willighagen became the new project leader
	and a start was made with integrating Jmol with
	<a href="http://cdk.sf.net/">The Chemical Development Kit</a>,
	something that was already planned in September 2000 by Dan, Egon
	and Christoph Steinbeck. 
      </p>
    </section>

    <section title="Jmol - an open source replacement for the Chime plugin">

      <p>
	Miguel joined the project at the end of 2002, with the explicit
	goal of helping build Jmol into a viable repacement for the
	Chime plugin (<a href="http://www.mdlchime.com">www.mdlchime.com</a>)
      </p>
      <p>
	In the first few months Miguel contributed the Spanish translation
	and made an initial pass at the RasMol/Chime script interpreter.
	He then some performance improvements and began working on rendering
	performance and speed.
      </p>
      <p>
	It quickly became apparent that the Java2D graphics did not
	provide the performance and functionality
	needed. In addition, it became clear that the core Jmol classes
	would not support the performance and space requirements for
	working with macromolecules with 10s of thousands of atoms.
      </p>
      <p>
	In the spring of 2003 Miguel began designing and implementing
	a high-performance software-based graphics engine. In order to
	ensure web deployment of the Jmol applet it was important
	that the engine run on version 1.1 Java Virtual Machines and
	that no specialized graphics hardware be required.
      </p>
      <p>
	Miguel also rewrote the core classes in order to support
	much larger molecules. In addition, he separated all file
	IO from the Jmol core, making it much easier to support
	new file types.
      </p>
      <p>
	An extended test period began at the end of 2003. During 2004
	a small set of users around the world contributed to Jmol
	development by testing Jmol, explaining chemical concepts,
	and explaining scripting behaviors of RasMol and Chime.
      </p>
      <p>
	Jmol version 10, an open source replacement for the Chime plugin,
	was released in December 2004.
      </p>
    </section>
    <section title="Jmol Literature">
      <p>
        An up to date list of literature describing Jmol can be found at
        <a href="http://wiki.jmol.org/index.php/Literature">http://wiki.jmol.org/index.php/Literature</a>.
      </p>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>


