<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<document>
  <body>
    <title>History</title>
    
    <section title="The origins of Jmol">

      <p>
        Jmol was originally intended to be a fully functional replacement for
        XMol which was a molecular viewing program developed at the Minnesota
        Supercomputer Center. Although the program executables were
        distributed, the source code was not available to users, and since the
        program has not been maintained, the free binary versions have become
        obsolete. For example, the SGI version of XMol does not run on IRIX 6.x
        because IRIX has switched to a new executable format.
      </p>
      
      <p>
        XMol's demise left a need for a similar tool. Dan Gezelter, the
        originator of Jmol, chose to avoid the same problems by making
        Jmol open source.  Although it has not
        completely met the goal of functionally replacing XMol, Jmol duplicates many
        of the most useful features, and in some ways, it has surpassed XMol
        functionality. In time, Jmol was hoped to include even more advanced
        features.
      </p>

      <p>
        Jmol was started as an OpenScience project which is dedicated to
        writing and releasing free and open source scientific software. For more
        information about the OpenScience project, go to
        <url>http://www.openscience.org/</url>.
      </p>
      
      <p>
        Later, Bradley A. Smith took over the project and did a lot of work in 
        streamlining the project as well as the software. Under his leadership
        new releases found its way to the user base, and many new features were
        added, some of which contributed by users.
      </p>
      
      <p>
	In the end of 2002, Egon Willighagen became the new project leader
	and a start was made with integrating Jmol with
	<a href="http://cdk.sf.net/">The Chemical Development Kit</a>,
	something that was already planned in September 2000 by Dan, Egon
	and Christoph Steinbeck. Since then Jmol has been ported to CDK for 
	about 80%. In the same period Miguel Howard
	completely rewrote the graphical engine of Jmol and implemented
        the RasMol/Chime script interpreter, making Jmol a viable
	alternative to the Chime plugin.
      </p>
    </section>
    <section title="Jmol Literature">
      <p>
        E.L. Willighagen, Processing CML Conventions in Java,
        <i>Internet Journal of Chemistry</i>, 4, <b>2001</b><br/>
        <ul>
          Describes how Jmol reads CML. (<a href="http://www.ijc.com/abstracts/abstract4n4.html">abstract</a>)
        </ul>
      </p>
      <p>
        Christoph Steinbeck, Yongquan Han, Stefan Kuhn, Oliver Horlacher, Edgar Luttmann, and Egon Willighagen,
        The Chemistry Development Kit (CDK): An Open-Source Java Library for Chemo- and Bioinformaticsm,
        <i>J.Chem.Inf.Comp.Sci.</i>, <b>2003</b><br/>
        <ul>
          Describes CDK the library on which Jmol is build. (<a href="http://pubs.acs.org/cgi-bin/abstract.cgi/jcisd8/2003/43/i02/abs/ci025584y.html">abstract</a>)
        </ul>
      </p>
      <p>
        Peter Murray-Rust, Henry S. Rzepa, Mark J. Williamson, and Egon L. Willighagen,
        Chemical Markup, XML, and the World Wide Web. 5. Applications of Chemical Metadata in RSS Aggregators,
        <i>J.Chem.Inf.Comp.Sci.</i>, <b>2004</b><br/>
        <ul>
          Describes a CDK plugin that acts as a RSS agregator and show its application as
          pluged in Jmol. (<a href="http://pubs.acs.org/cgi-bin/asap.cgi/jcisd8/asap/abs/ci034244p.html">abstract</a>)
        </ul>
      </p>
      <p>
        Please send additions too <a href="mailto:jmol-developers@lists.sf.net">jmol-developers@lists.sf.net</a>.
      </p>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>









