<?xml version="1.0"?>
<book>
  <bookinfo>
    <title>JMol Applet Documentation</title>
  </bookinfo>
  
  <chapter>
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>
      The JMol Applet is an offshoot of the main Jmol application, allowing
      the display of 3D chemical information from within any Java 1.1 enabled
      browser.
    </para>
  </chapter>
  
  <chapter>
    <title>Jmol Applet Usage</title>
    <section>
      <title>Embedding the Jmol Applet in a Web Page</title>
      <para>
        To embed the Jmol Applet in a web page, you need a number of 
        java "jar" files.  These contain the JmolApplet program.  The first two
        files are required for the applet to function at all, while the other
        two are only required for loading CML formatted chemical data files.
      </para>
      <para>
        The core jar files are:
      <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>JmolApplet.jar</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>vecmath1.1-1.12.jar</para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      </para>
      <para>
        The CML jar files are:
      <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>sax.jar</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>aelfred.jar</para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      </para>
      <para>
        These need to be somewhere on your website where they can be read by
        someone surfing your site.  Next, insert the following code into the
        relevant part of your web page:
      </para>
      <para>
        &lt APPLET CODE="org.openscience.miniJmol.JmolApplet.class"
          ARCHIVE="JmolApplet.jar,vecmath1.1-1.12.jar"
          WIDTH=400 HEIGHT=400 ALIGN="LEFT" &gt
          &lt PARAM NAME=MODEL VALUE="caffeine.xyz" &gt
          &lt PARAM NAME=FORMAT VALUE="XYZ" &gt
          &lt PARAM NAME=ATOMTYPES VALUE="Atomtypes" &gt
        &lt /APPLET &gt
      </para>
      <para>
        Here, the ARCHIVE points to where the jar files are located on your
        website.  You also need to add sax.jar and aelfred.jar for CML files.
        The WIDTH, HEIGHT and ALIGN parameters are all part of the APPLET tag,
        and are documented in any HTML reference book.  WIDTH and HEIGHT will
        determine the size of the box that Jmol has to play with.  The ALIGN
        tag can be set top a number of different values, but the most useful
        are LEFT (in which case text wraps around the right side of Jmol),
        RIGHT (in which case text wraps around the left side of Jmol),
        and BASELINE (in which case there will be no text to the left or right
        of the Jmol applet.
      </para>
      <para>
        The tags PARAM NAME= VALUE= combinations are passed directly to Jmol,
        and are not interpreted by the web browser.  There are a number of
        different parameters, which are described in the next section.  The
        most important ones are MODEL, FORMAT and ATOMTYPES.  For many types
        of atom files, it is only necessary to specify the MODEL parameter,
        which should be the URL of the chemical file that you wish to display.
        Supported formats are:
        <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para>CML</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>Gaussian 98</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>PDB</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>XYZ</para></listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </para>
      <para>
        Additionally, the FORMAT parameter can be set to CMLSTRING, in which
        case the MODEL parameter is assumed to contain the entire CML file,
        not a URL.  Example: &lt PARAM NAME=FORMAT VALUE="CMLSTRING" &gt
      </para>
      <para>
        Previous versions of the Jmol Applet required the ATOMTYPES parameter
        to be set, to define the size and color that the various different
        atomic species would be drawn.  Now, if the ATOMTYPES parameter is
        not specified, a default set of colors and sizes are used.
        However, it is always useful to be able to adjust how atoms appear on
        the screen, or to add elements which are not included in the default
        atom definitions.
      </para>
      <para>
        To specify your own atomtypes, simply set the ATOMTYPES parameter to
        the URL of a file containing the atom type information.  This file
        is a text file, with a line for each atom type definition.  Columns
        are seperated by whitespace (tabs and/or spaces).  In order, the columns
        are: AtomType(1), BaseAtomType(2), AtomicNumber(3), Mass(4), vanDerWallRadius(5), covalentRadius(6), ColorRed(7), ColorGreen(8), ColorBlue(9).
      </para>
      <para>
        The AtomType column contains the name of the atom type in the same
        format as contained in your data file.  The BaseAtomType then contains
        the atom symbol for the type.  The color that the atom will be drawn
        in is determined by the 3 color columns.  These values should be in
        the range 0 to 255.  Here are some sample lines out of the atom types
        file:
        <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para>C1 C 6 12.011 1.50 0.77 255 0 0</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>C2 C 6 12.011 1.65 0.77 0 255 0</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>C3 C 6 12.011 1.65 0.77 0 0 255</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>He He 2 4.003 1.40 0.93 255 255 255</para></listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        Here, the three different types C1, C2 and C3 all represent carbon.
        But if you want to draw sp1, sp2 and sp3 bonded atoms in different
        colors, you can change your atom file to have C1, C2 and C3
        representing the different bond hybridisations.  The sample atom
        file above would show C sp1 in red, C sp2 in green and C sp3 in blue.
        Helium atoms would be shown in white.
      </para>
    </section>
    <title>Jmol Applet Parameters</title>
    <section>
      <para>
        The complete list of Jmol Applet parameters (as of 16th September 2000) is:
        <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para>BCOLOUR - The color of the background</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>FCOLOUR - The color of the labels, etc.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>STYLE - The rendering style, can be SHADED, WIREFRAME or QUICKDRAW</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>WIREFRAMEROTATION - Can be ON or OFF, default is ON</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>BONDS - Display bonds ?  can be ON, OFF or NEVER.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>ZOOM - How much the initial zoom is, defaults to 1</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>ATOMSIZE - A factor to increase the size of the atoms (not the same as ZOOM), defaults to 1</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>CUSTOMVIEWS - Contains a formatted string which sets up buttons for custom rotations, zooms and frame selection.</para></listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </para>
      <para>
        STYLE - specifies the initial rendering style, which can be
        subsequently changed by the user.
      </para>
      <para>
        BONDS - specifies whether bonds should be initially shown or not.  The
        special value NEVER means that bonds can not be toggled by the user.
        This value is available, since large chemical files may be slow to
        load because of Jmol attempting to calculate the atomic bonds.
      </para>
      <para>
        ZOOM - specifies a factor for the initial zoom.  However, this seems
        to be a little bit buggy.  A value of 1.2 will give you more zoom,
        while 0.8 will give you less zoom, etc.  However, value far away from
        1.0 may mess up the perspective a little bit.
      </para>
      <para>
        ATOMSIZE - specifies a factor for increasing the size of rendered atoms.
        This does not change the bond sizes, or do any zooming.
      </para>
      <para>
        CUSTOMVIEWS - specifies a list of buttons that will appear at the top
        of the Jmol box.  Each of these buttons can do custom zooming, rotating,
        translating and frame selection.  The format of this parameter is:
      </para>
      <para>
        VALUE="Button 1 Name{Button1Action1;Button1Action2;...}Button 2 Name{Button2Action1;...}..."
      </para>
      <para>
        The text "Button 1 Name" will appear on the button.  This text may
        have spaces in it, but cannot contain the { or } characters.
        The set of actions within the braces will be performed when the button
        is pressed.  The actions must be separated by semicolons, and cannot
        have spaces embedded in them.  Valid actions are:
        <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para>HOME - Resets rotation, translation and zoom to the original values</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>FRAME=frameno - Selects frame "frameno" from a multi-frame chemical file</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>ZOOM=factor - Zooms by the specified factor</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>TRANSLATE=dx,dy - Translates the view by (dx,dy).</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>ROTATE=ry1,rx,ry2 - Rotates the frame around the y-axis by ry1 degrees, followed by rotate around x-axis of ry degrees, followed by another y-axis rotation of ry2 degrees.  This allows for any rotation to be specified.</para></listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </para>
      <section>
        <title>Atom Style</title>
        <section>
          <title>Quick Draw</title>
          <para>
            Views molecules without shading. Preferred on slower
            computers.
          </para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>Shading</title>
          <para>
            Views molecules with shading. Since this takes more
            calculations, this only works well on faster computers.
          </para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>Wire Frame</title>	  
        </section>
      </section>      
      <section>
        <title>Bond Style</title>
        <section>
          <title>Quick Draw</title>	  
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>Shading</title>	  
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>Wire Frame</title>	  
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>Lines</title>	  
        </section>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Atom Labels</title>
        <section>
          <title>No Atom Labels</title>	  
          <para>
            View the atoms without any label.
          </para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>Atomic Symbols</title>	  
          <para>
            Label the atoms with their symbol.
          </para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>Atom Types</title>
          <para>
            Label the atoms with their atom type.
          </para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>Atom Numbers</title>	  
        </section>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Property Labels</title>
        <section>
          <title>None</title>	  
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>
  </chapter>

</book>
