<chapter>
<title>Jmol Applet Usage</title>
<section>
  <title>Embedding the Jmol Applet in a Web Page</title>
  <para>
    To embed the Jmol Applet in a web page, you need only one
    java archive file, <emphasis>JmolApplet.jar</emphasis>. All classes
    and data files are included in this file. Put this file in the
    directory on your webserver. 
  </para>
  <para>
    The name of the applet class is <emphasis>JmolApplet</emphasis>.
  </para>
  <para>
    The Jmol applet can be embedded in html pages using the 
    APPLET html tag:
    <programlisting><![CDATA[
      <applet code="JmolApplet" archive="JmolApplet.jar"
	width="350" height="350">
	<param name="load" value="caffeine.xyz">
	</applet>
	]]>
    </programlisting>
  </para>
  <para>
    CODE identifies the name of the class, in this case 'JmolApplet' or
    'JmolApplet.class'. ARCHIVE identifies the name of the jar file
    where the classes for this applet are to be found. WIDTH and HEIGHT
    specify the dimensions of the applet within the html page in pixels.
  </para>
  <para>
    The PARAM tags are used to pass parameters to the applet. 
    The LOAD parameter specifies the URL of the molecule file which
    should be loaded. 
  </para>
  <para>
    The following is a slightly more complicated version with a few
    more options:
    <programlisting><![CDATA[
      <applet name="jmol" code="JmolApplet" archive="JmolApplet.jar"
	width="350" height="350" align="right">
	<param name="load"    value="molecules/caffeine.xyz">
	<param name="bgcolor" value="#DDDDFF">
	<param name="style"   value="quickdraw">
	<param name="label"   value="symbol">
	<param name="script"  value="move 0 0 360 0 0 0 0 0 5">
	<param name="wireframeRotation" value="true">
	<param name="perspectiveDepth"  value="false">
        </applet>
        ]]>
    </programlisting>
  </para>
  <para>
    In this case the applet is given a name so that it can be referenced
    from JavaScript code (applet="jmol"). The applet is aligned to the
    right side of the page so that text flows to the left (align="right").
    Using additional parameters (&lt;param name="*" value="*"&gt;)
    a molecule is loaded from a relative URL on the web server
    (molecules/caffeine.xyz),
    the background color is set to a light blue (#DDDDFF),
    the style is set so that shaded atoms/bonds are not used (quickdraw),
    atoms are labeled with their atomic symbol (symbol),
    a script is run which rotates 360 degrees around the z axis in 5
    seconds,
    wireframeRotation is turned on so that all movements
    are done in wireframe mode,
    and perspective depth is turned off so that the molecule rendering is
    a flat projection to the screen with no size adjustment for atoms
    and bonds further away from the viewer. 
  </para>
</section>
<section>
  <title>Jmol Applet Parameters</title>
  <para>
    The complete list of Jmol Applet parameters is as follows:
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  bgcolor - The color of the background: official html
	  color names or #RRGGBB notation
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  style - The rendering style for atoms and bonds:
	  SHADED, WIREFRAME or QUICKDRAW
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  label - The rendering style for atom labels:
	  NONE, SYMBOL or NUMBER
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  wireframeRotation - Rotations use wireframe for faster rendering:
	  TRUE or FALSE (defaults to FALSE)
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  perspectiveDepth - Rotations use wireframe for faster rendering:
	  TRUE or FALSE (defaults to TRUE)
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  script - RasMol/Chime script commands to execute
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </para>
  <section>
    <title>style</title>
    <section>
      <title>shaded</title>
      <para>
	Renders atoms and bonds as shaded spheres and cylinders. 
	Shaded images are calculated and cached, so performance
	should not be an issue except when dealing with very
	large protein molecules. 
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>quickdraw</title>
      <para>
	Renders atoms and bonds as flat, solid-colored circles
	and rectangles. 
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>wireframe</title>
      <para>
	Atoms are drawn as unfilled circles. Bonds are drawn as
	single lines. 
      </para>
      <para>
	Note: If rendering performance is unacceptably slow when dealing
	with very large molecules, the WIREFRAMEROTATION option can be
	used to switch to wireframe mode during rotations and translations.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Atom Labels</title>
    <section>
      <title>none</title>
      <para>
	View the atoms without any label. This is the default. 
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>symbol</title>
      <para>
	Label the atoms with their element symbol. 
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>number</title>
      <para>
	Label the atoms with their index number. 
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>
</section>
<section>
  <title>script</title>
  <para>
    The script parameter allows you to specify a script of
    RasMol/Chime commands to be executed after the molecule file
    is loaded.
  </para>
  <para>
    Multiple script commands can be separated by the semicolon (;)
    character.
  </para>
</section>
</chapter>
