<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<document>
	<body>
		<title>Jmol: an open-source browser-based HTML5 viewer and stand-alone Java viewer for chemical structures in 3D</title>
		<header>
			<div style="float:right; position:relative; top:-1em;"><img src="images/Jmol_icon_128.png" alt="Jmol icon" title="" />
			</div>
			<h2 style="margin-top:0;padding-top:0;">with features for molecules, crystals, materials, and biomolecules
			
			<br /><br /><a href="https://sourceforge.net/projects/jmol/files/Jmol/">Jmol/JSmol Download Page</a>
			(jsmol.zip is contained within Jmol-xx.xx.xx-binary.zip)
			
			
			<br /><br /><a href="https://chemapps.stolaf.edu/jmol/docs/">Jmol/JSmol scripting documentation</a>
			
			
			</h2>
			<hr/>
		</header>
		<section title="Overview">
			<p>
	Jmol is a free, open source molecule viewer for students,
	educators, and researchers in chemistry, biochemistry, physics, and materials science.
	It is cross-platform, running on Windows, Mac OS X, and Linux/Unix systems. 
			</p>
			<ul>
				<li>
	    The <b>JSmol JmolApplet</b> is a web browser JavaScript application that can be
	    integrated easily into web pages. Though Java-based for development and management, 
	    JSmol is completely JavaScript. 
	  </li>
				<li>
	    The <b>Jmol application</b> is a stand-alone Java application (Jmol.jar)
	    that runs on the desktop. It has all the capabilities of the JSmol applet but runs approximately 3-6 times faster.
	    In addition, it can be run in "headless" mode (<b>JmolData.jar</b>) in order to carry out tasks that need to be replicated.
	  </li>
				<li>
	    <b>Jmol.jar</b> can be integrated into any other Java program, providing file loading, structure processing, viewing, and output capabilities. 
	  </li>
	  <li>
	  Jmol is <b>fully scriptable</b>. For the most up-to-date scripting documentation see the 
	  <a href="https://chemapps.stolaf.edu/jmol/docs/">Jmol/JSmol interactive scripting documentation</a>.  
	  </li>
			</ul>
		</section>
		<section title="How to cite Jmol">
			<p>The recommended way to cite Jmol is:<br/>
				<b>Jmol: an open-source Java viewer for chemical structures in 3D. http://www.jmol.org/ 
	</b>
			</p>
			<p>Remember to always use uppercase '<b>J</b>', lowercase '<b>mol</b>' 
	(<a href="./faqs/index.en.html#How%20do%20you%20write%20Jmol?">explanation</a>).
	</p>
			<p>If you prefer, a list of articles that describe Jmol can be found in the 
	<a href="http://wiki.jmol.org/index.php/Literature">Jmol Literature</a> section of the Jmol Wiki.
	</p>
		</section>
		<section title="What Jmol can do">
			<section title="Samples">
				<p>
				Check out the <a href="./screenshots/">Screenshot Gallery</a>
				(still images) to see samples of what can be done with Jmol
				<br/>
				and the <a href="https://chemapps.stolaf.edu/jmol/jsmol">Demonstration pages</a>
				especially <a href="https://chemapps.stolaf.edu/jmol/jsmol/jsmol.htm">jsmol.htm</a>
				<a href="https://chemapps.stolaf.edu/jmol/jsmol/simple.htm">simple.htm</a>
				<a href="https://chemapps.stolaf.edu/jmol/jsmol/simple2.htm">simple2.htm</a>
				<a href="https://chemapps.stolaf.edu/jmol/jsmol/jsmetest2.htm">jsmetest2.htm</a>
				<a href="https://chemapps.stolaf.edu/jmol/jsmol/jsv_predict2.htm">jsv_predict2.htm</a>
				
				to see buttons and menus in action (interactive applet).
			</p>
			</section>
			<section title="Features">
				<ul>
					<li>
	  Free, open-source software licensed under the 
	  <a href="www.gnu.org/licenses/licenses.html#LGPL">
	    GNU Lesser General Public License
	  </a>
					</li>
					<li>
	  Applet, Application, and Systems Integration Component
	  				<ul>
							<li>
	      The <b>JmolApplet</b> is a web browser applet that can be
	      integrated into web pages. It is ideal for development
	      of web-based courseware and web-accessible
	      chemical databases. The JmolApplet provides an upgrade path
	      for users of the <a href="http://www.mdli.com">Chime</a> plug-in. 
	    </li>
							<li>
	      The <b>Jmol application</b> is a standalone Java application
	      that runs on the desktop. 
	    </li>
							<li>
	      The <b>JmolViewer</b> can be integrated as a component
	      into other Java applications.
	    </li>
						</ul>
					</li>
					<li>
	  Multi-language
	  				<ul>
	  					<li>
	  Translated into multiple languages: 
Catalan (ca),
Chinese (both zh_CN and zh_TW)
Czech (cs),
Dutch (nl),
Finnish (fi)
French (fr),
German (de),
Hungarian (hu),
Indonesian (id),
Italian (it),
Korean (ko),
Malay (ms),
Portuguese - Brazil (pt_BR),
Spanish (es),
Turkish (tr),
Ukrainian (uk)
	 (in addition to the native American English, en-US, and British English, en-GB).
	  					</li>
	  					<li>
	  Automatically adopts the language of the user's
	  operating system, if it is among the translations available.
	  You can change to another language if desired.
	  					</li>
	  					<li>
	For up-to-date details or instructions for adding your language,
	see <a href="http://wiki.jmol.org/index.php/Internationalisation">the Wiki</a>.
	  					</li>
	  				</ul>
					</li>
					<li>
	  Cross-platform
	  				<ul>
							<li>Windows</li>
							<li>Mac OS X</li>
							<li>Linux / Unix</li>
						</ul>
					</li>
					<li>
	  Supports all major web browsers: Internet Explorer, Mozilla and Firefox,
    Safari, Google Chrome, Opera, Konqueror, IceWeasel, ...
					</li>
					<li>
	  High-performance 3D rendering with no hardware requirements
	</li>

					<li>
	  See <a href="https://chemapps.stolaf.edu/jmol/docs/#loadfiletypes">the scripting documentation</a> and also the <a href="http://wiki.jmol.org/index.php/File_formats">Jmol Wiki file format page</a> for  
	  complete details on file types that Jmol can read. Note that files which are compressed using gzip will automatically be decompressed.
					</li>

					<li>
	  Animations
	</li>
					<li>
	  Vibrations
	</li>
					<li>
	  Surfaces
	</li>
					<li>
	  Orbitals
	</li>
					<li>
	  Support for unit cell and symmetry operations
	</li>
					<li>
	  Schematic shapes for secondary structures in biomolecules, including <a href="http://jmol.x3dna.org/">DSSR</a> for investigating the secondary structure of nucleic acids. 
	</li>
					<li>
	  Measurements
	  <ul>
							<li>distance</li>
							<li>angle</li>
							<li>torsion angle</li>
						</ul>
					</li>
					<li>
	  Support for RasMol/Chime scripting language 
	</li>
					<li>
	  Exports to jpg, png, pngj (a png image that can be dragged back into Jmol to reproduce the exact model state the image was created from) gif, ppm, pdf, POV-Ray, Gaussian, Maya, vrml, x3d, idtf, web page.
	</li>
				</ul>
			</section>
		</section>
		<section title="Learn to use Jmol">
			<section title="Manuals and tutorials">
				<p>A <a href="http://biomodel.uah.es/anun/manual-jmol/inicio-en.htm">handbook</a> has been published for learning Jmol, and there are also <a href="http://wiki.jmol.org/index.php/Literature">other publications</a> about Jmol.
	</p>
				<p>There is also a list of <a href="http://wiki.jmol.org/index.php/Main_Page">tutorials</a> designed to 
	learn the use of Jmol, and more help, within <a href="http://wiki.jmol.org/">Jmol Wiki</a>. 
	</p>
				<p>Finally, there is a <a href="./docs/">documentation</a> section in this web site, for more technical details. 
	</p>
			</section>
			<section title="Learn by example">
				<p>You can also learn by examining web pages that use Jmol: <a href="./demo/">demonstration pages</a> within this 
	web site, and a list of <a href="http://wiki.jmol.org/index.php/Websites_Using_Jmol">websites using Jmol</a> in Jmol Wiki.
	</p>
			</section>
			<section title="Jmol community">
				<section title="Jmol Wiki">
					<p>A user-maintained site collecting a lot of information about the use of Jmol. 
	<i>More dynamical and frequently updated than this web site!</i>
		-- <a href="http://wiki.jmol.org/">visit Jmol Wiki</a>
					</p>
				</section>
				<section title="Mailing lists">
					<p>
	Those with interest in molecular visualization, especially
	the education and research communities, are encouraged
	to join the <b>jmol-users</b> mailing list or even the 
	<b>jmol-developers</b> mailing list.
	There you can share ideas and experiences, ask for help,
	give us feedback, request new features or changes, 
	discuss implementation, submit patches, or contribute code.
	</p>
					<p>
	Without subscribing to any lists, you can also search the archives that collect all messages posted to the lists. 
	</p>
					<p>
	For more information, please visit the <a href="./project/">Project pages</a> section.
	</p>
				</section>
			</section>
		</section>
	</body>
</document>
