<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<document>
  <body>
    <title>Jmol v10 Beta Test Program</title>
    
    <section title="Jmol v10 Beta Testing">

      <p>
	Jmol v10 is a complete rewrite of most of Jmol.
	Major features/changes include:
	<ul>
	  <li>substantial performance improvements</li>
	  <li>true 3d graphics engine</li>
	  <li>support for macromolecule secondary structure graphics</li>
	  <li>additional script commands</li>
	  <li>support for the RasMol/Chime coordinate system orientation</li>
	  <li>JmolAppletControl buttons</li>
	</ul>
      </p>
      <p>
	Along with these new features comes a new set of bugs.
	Thank you for helping us test out new releases of Jmol and
	helping us find these bugs.
      </p>

      <p>
	<i>
	  At this point, we feel obligated to admit that this is not
	  really being conducted as a formal <strong>beta test.</strong>
	  During the test phase we are continuing to make substantial
	  changes to the code; changes that go far beyond a beta test.
	  But we are continuing to develop and enhance the code,
	  regardless of what we call it.
	</i>
      </p>

      <section title="Bug reporting procedures">
	<p>
	  If you can, please submit bugs directly into the bug tracking
	  database provided by sourceforge. This will save us a little
	  time and, most importantly, will ensure that your bugs do not
	  get lost.
	</p>
	<p>
	  <a href=
	     "http://sourceforge.net/tracker/?group_id=23629&amp;atid=379133"
	  ><b>Jmol Bug Tracking Database</b></a>
	</p>
      </section>
      
      <section title="Support and communications">
	<p>
	During the test program, support will be provided through the
	<b>jmol-users@lists.sf.net</b> mailing list. If you are not on
	the list and would like to subscribe you can go to
	<a href="http://lists.sourceforge.net/lists/listinfo/jmol-users"
	><b>this page to subscribe</b></a>
	</p>
      </section>
      
      <section title="Release/distribution mechanism">
	<p>
	  Test releases will be made on this page. Releases will be a single
	  .zip file that contains test prerelease. You can unzip this file
	  using standard tools, including unzip, pkunzip, winzip, and jar.
	  We do not plan to release sample files or support code. For those
	  who are interested, source code is always available through
	  anonymous CVS checkout. 
	</p>
      </section>
    </section>
      
    <section title="Jmol10pre7">
      <p>
	Jmol version 10 pre-release 7 was released on 22 Mar 2004.
	This release includes
	the following enhancements:
	<ul>
	  <li>support for wheel mouse on JVM 1.4 and greater</li>
	  <li>support for CTL-click to bring up popup menu on Mac OS.</li>
	  <li>
	    support for distance/angle/torsion measurements using dbl-click
	    <br />
	    <i>Please be on the lookout for mouse gesture bugs</i>
	  </li>
	  <li>support for ShelX .res files</li>
	  <li>occupancy as an atom property</li>
	  <li>corrected bugs in atom expressions with chains x, y, or z</li>
	  <li>
	    ability to redirect *echo* output to the Applet window<br />
	    <i>
	      set echo {top|middle|bottom|none|off} {left|center|right}<br />
	      echo Hello World!
	    </i>
	  </li>
	  <li>
	    label colors and fonts are individually controllable, according
	    to the selection set.
	  </li>
	  <li>
	    support for 'font' as an extended command <br />
	    <i>
	      font {object} {points} {Serif|SansSerif|Monospaced}
	      {Normal|Bold|Italic|BoldItalic}<br />
	      font label 12<br />
	      font echo 14 SansSerif Bold
	    </i>
	  </li>
	  <li>browser status line is updated when an atom is picked</li>
	</ul>
	This release continues to have the
	following functional limitations:
	<ul>
	  <li>Now only supports .xyz, .mol, .pdb, and .res files</li>
	  <li>Does not have full animation support</li>
	  <li>Does not handle vibrations</li>
	  <li>Does not have full crystal cell support</li>
	  <li>
	    Will not automatically recognize protein secondary structures
	  </li>
	  <li>Will not render isosurfaces</li>
	  <li>Does not handle nucleotide graphic shapes</li>
	</ul>
      </p>
      <p>
	<a href="Jmol10pre7.zip">
	  <font size="+1">
	    <i>Give me the code!</i>
	    Jmol10pre7.zip
	  </font>
	</a>
      </p>
      <p>
	<a href="Jmol10pre6.zip">
	  <font size="-1">
	    <i>Give me the old code</i> Jmol10pre6.zip
	  </font>
	</a>
      </p>
      <p>
	Unzip the code using the tool of your choice. It will unzip into
	a subdirectory of the current directory.
      </p>
      <p>
	The Java <b>jar</b> tool will work fine since a .jar is the same
	format as .zip : <b>jar xf Jmol10pre7.zip</b>
      </p>
      <p>
	To run the jmol application you can type: <b>java -jar Jmol.jar</b>
	<br/>With most GUIs, you also be able to double-click on Jmol.jar
	to launch it. (If this doesn't work then create an association
	for files with the extension .jar)
      </p>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
