<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<document>
  <body>
    <title>Jmol v10 Beta Test Program</title>
    
    <section title="Jmol v10 Beta Testing">

      <p>
	Jmol v10 is a complete rewrite of Jmol.
	Major features/changes include:
	<ul>
	  <li>dramatic performance improvements</li>
	  <li>true 3d graphics engine that requires no special hardware</li>
	  <li>support for macromolecule secondary structure graphics</li>
	  <li>compatibility with existing RasMol/Chime scripts</li>
	  <li>
	    JavaScript library to facilitate web application developement
	  </li>
	</ul>
      </p>
      <p>
	<i>
	  <b>Jmol version 10 will be released in December 2004.</b>
	  Please do your best to find and report bugs
	  ... and have fun!
	</i>
      </p>

      <section title="Bug reporting procedures">
	<p>
	  If you can, please submit bugs directly into the bug tracking
	  database provided by sourceforge. This will save us a little
	  time and, most importantly, will ensure that your bugs do not
	  get lost.
	</p>
	<p>
	  <a href=
	     "http://sourceforge.net/tracker/?group_id=23629&amp;atid=379133"
	  ><b>Jmol Bug Tracking Database</b></a>
	</p>
      </section>
      
      <section title="Support and communications">
	<p>
	  During the test program, support will be provided through the
	  <b>jmol-users@lists.sf.net</b> mailing list. If you are not on
	  the list and would like to subscribe you can go to
	  <a href="http://lists.sourceforge.net/lists/listinfo/jmol-users"
	  ><b>this page to subscribe</b></a>
	</p>
      </section>
      
      <section title="Release/distribution mechanism">
	<p>
	  Test releases will be made on this page. Releases will be a single
	  .zip file that contains test prerelease. You can unzip this file
	  using standard tools, including unzip, pkunzip, winzip, and jar.
	  We do not plan to release sample files or support code. For those
	  who are interested, source code is always available through
	  anonymous CVS checkout. 
	</p>
      </section>
    </section>
    
    <section title="Jmol10pre23">
      <p>
	Jmol version 10 pre-release 23 was released on Fri 10 Dec 2004.
	<ul>
	  <li>
	    Browsers with Java 1.4 can now pop up a command line console!
	    The console can also be opened from a script using
	    <code>console [on|off]</code>
	  </li>
	  <li>
	    Basic molecular model data can now be seen in the popup menu
	  </li>
	  <li>
	    Molecular model files can now be downloaded through
	    the popup menu!
	  </li>
	  <li>
	    JmolAppletControl support was re-introduced
	  </li>
	  <li>
	    Jmol.js API change - jmolApplet no longer takes a molecular
	    model file name. Load your file as part of the script
	  </li>
	  <li>
	    Support for <code>frank</code> and <code>debugscript</code>
	    was dropped from applet param tags
	  </li>
	  <li>
	    CML files can now be read on 1.1 JVMs
	    (Win32 &amp;&amp; ((IE &amp;&amp; MSFT JVM) || NS47))
	    using the Gnu Aelfred2 XML parser. <i>Note that gnujaxp.jar
	    must be explicitly included in the <code>archive</code>
	    attribute string value</i>
	  </li>
	  <li>
	    The <code>load</code> param tag to the applet is now
	    deprecated. Users are encouraged to load their model
	    file as part of their <code>script</code>
	  </li>
	  <li>
	    bug fixed - 'frank'/logo was sometimes not displayed
	  </li>
	  <li>
	    bug fixed - measured angle text was sometimes not displayed
	    during rotation
	  </li>
	  <li>
	    bug fixed - hover text was sometimes not displayed when slab
	    was on
	  </li>
	  <li>
	    bug fixed - moveTo went berzerk when model was already
	    in the target orientation and the rotation angle was 0 degrees
	  </li>
	  <li>
	    bug fixed - when loading the JmolApplet with separate
	    'load' and 'script' params, the default style
	    of the molecular model (spacefill 20%; wireframe 0.1; color cpk)
	    was sometimes visible before your script executed
	  </li>
	</ul>
      </p>
      <p>
	<a href="Jmol10pre23.zip">
	  <font size="+1">
	    <i>Give me the code!</i>
	    Jmol10pre23.zip
	  </font>
	</a>
      </p>
      <p>
	<a href="Jmol10pre22.zip">
	  <font size="-1">
	    <i>Give me the old code</i> Jmol10pre22.zip
	  </font>
	</a>
      </p>
      <p>
	Unzip the code using the tool of your choice. It will unzip into
	a subdirectory of the current directory.
      </p>
      <p>
	The Java <b>jar</b> tool will work fine since a .jar is the same
	format as .zip : <b>jar xf Jmol10pre23.zip</b>
      </p>
      <p>
	To run the jmol application you can type: <b>java -jar Jmol.jar</b>
	<br/>With most GUIs, you also be able to double-click on Jmol.jar
	to launch it. (If this doesn't work then create an association
	for files with the extension .jar)
      </p>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
